Miguel Rivera-Lanas

Data scientist/engineer with 4 years experience in investment management. Interested in research roles focusing on ML/AI bias and computational social science. Primarily focused on empirical methods to study quantitative and social effects of disinformation propagation and content moderation systems.

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist / Engineer — **Point72,** NYC, NY September 2019 - Present

- Sept 2019 to Aug. 2020, I was part of a research and learning group, investigating use cases for using novel data sets, including credit-card transaction panel data, website traffic, cell-phone geolocation panels, and others for discovering trends related to fundamental KPIs for companies.
- In Sept. 2020, I joined an investment team with 8 sector analysts, where I manage all data science and engineering projects.
- Implement statistical descriptive modeling, preprocessing, feature
 engineering, and forecasting over a diverse range of data sets related to oil
 well production, retail consumer trends, and other sectors.
- Analyze sector exposure to risk factors, inter sector correlations, and build systematic strategy backtesting framework
- Build scalable and robust cloud based event-driven ETL architecture for delivering continuous reporting of data products

Research Associate, Fixed Income — AllianceBernstein, NYC, NY June 2016 - August 2016, June 2017 - August 2019

- Rotations as research associate for macro economics, quantitative research, and portfolio strategy technology teams
- Developed and maintained ETL, preprocessing, and reporting for novel liquidity signals from live order-book data, utilized by traders to better assess supply and demand conditions for specific parts of the market.

Research Assistant — Wharton Management Dep., Philadelphia, PA September 2015 - May 2016

 Compiled original research on Canadian and Brazilian oil drilling infrastructure projects as part of a long term study focusing on project management best-practices. Used LexisNexis for primary source research on effects of macroeconomic trends and operational decisions.

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA — B.A., Cum Laude August 2013 - May 2017

Major: Economics, Minors(s): Statistics, International Relations

Clubs:

- Check One: Board Member. Student organization providing a space for discussions about personal and societal experiences about race and mixed-heritage backgrounds.
- Penn Journal of Economics: Editorial Committee. (PJE) is a semi-annual, peer-reviewed publication of honors theses and other academic projects for undergraduates and faculty.

Email: rivera.lanasm@gmail.com

Github: rivera-lanasm **Website:** rivera-lanasm.com

CORE COMPETENCIES

Scripting: Python, Scala, R

Development: Git, Airflow, Docker **Cloud:** AWS (S3, EC2, RDS, Lambda,

SNS, Glue Jobs)

Databases: PostgresSQL, MongoDB **ML:** Sklearn, Tensorflow, SpaCy **Data Manipulation:** Pandas, Numpy, SciPy, BeautifulSoup, Spark, Tidyverse

Web Dashboard: Plotly Dash

INTERESTS

Computational Social Science, Misinformation, Fairness and Bias in ML/AI

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Visit www.rivera-lanasm.com/post/

- Logic/Probability Puzzles:
- Logic and math puzzles solved with analytical and probabilistic methods. Solutions coded primarily in **Scala**.

VOLUNTEERING

- Statisticians without Borders
- Nov. 2020 March 2021
- Consulted NGO over 15 weeks as part of a volunteer team
- Implemented data pipelines tracking COVID-19 epidemiological model results for use by municipal health organizations in India.

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent), Spanish (Fluent), French (Working Proficiency)